Guide to the Charles Joseph Levy Collection of Victoriana
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Charles Joseph Levy Collection of Victoriana
1790-1973
1860-1900
GEN MSS 1280
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.74
(12 boxes)
The Charles Joseph Levy Collection of Victoriana contains printed material, including clippings, advertisements, and pictorial works; other ephemera, including objects; and a small amount of manuscript material, nearly all dating from the reign of Queen Victoria (1837-1901).
Levy, Charles Joseph, 1935-
Arrangement
Organized into four groups: I. Ephemera; II. Ephemera - Addenda; III. Material Not Listed by Levy; IV. Objects.
The collection is arranged in the order in which it was received. The descriptive categories and item descriptions are taken almost entirely from the original inventory by Charles Joseph Levy; no attempt has been made to standardize the language or style of the entries.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Joseph Levy Collection of Victoriana contains printed material, including clippings, advertisements, and pictorial works; other ephemera, including objects; and a small amount of manuscript material, nearly all dating from the reign of Queen Victoria (1837-1901).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 12 (glass negatives): Restricted Fragile Material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Charles Joseph Levy Collection of Victoriana is the gift of Charles Joseph Levy, 1977 and 1980.
Victoriana; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Ephemera (general object genre) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Glass negatives; Levy, Charles Joseph, 1935-
- Ephemera, Series I
  - Pictorial Material
    - Glass plates of the British army on parade and in action, undated (Box 12)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Stored in: Restricted Fragile, Box 12
    - Color caricature illustrating justice performed by a woman upon a man, circa 1825 (Box 1)
    - Pen and ink sketch of a highway robbery titled, "Very Deaf Indeed", circa 1830
    - Color plate from a dictionary of varieties of fish, undated
    - Fragment of a document in secretarial hand, with pen drawing of a seated king, undated
    - Color card of the British court in session, undated
    - Watercolor of a Scottish highlander, undated
    - 4 sandpictures of sites on the Isle of Wight, undated
    - Sketchbook containing 27 animal prints, undated
    - Color illustrations on board of "Richard Turpin plunging into the River Ouse..." and "Dick Turpin clearing the Old Hornsey Toll Bar Gate..." London: J. L. Marks., 1837 March 9, 1836 August 17 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Small sketch of "Miners at Schemnitz," London: Fisher, Son, and Co., 1832 (Box 1)
    - Mounted proof print of an Aubrey Beardsley design for "The Murder in the Rue Morgue", undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Mounted proof print of an Aubrey Beardsley design for "The Mask of the Red Death", undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Mounted proof print of an Aubrey Beardsley design for "The Fall of the House of Usher", undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Mounted proof print of an Aubrey Beardsley design for "The Black Cat", undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Print of "Two Kittens," from the original painting by Gustave de Jonghe, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Duelling print, circa 1790 (Box 1)
    - Small color print of Windsor Castle, undated
    - Color print of "Greenwich Hospital" by James Holland, undated
    - Color print of "The Houses of Parliament" after a photograph by G. W. Wilson & Co., Aberdeen, undated
    - Color print of "The Crystal Palace, Sydenham" after a photograph by J. Valentine & Son, Dundee, undated
    - "Victoria Greeted as Queen," by H. T. Wells, undated
    - "Queen Louise Visiting the Poor," by Hugo Handler, undated
    - Lithograph of "Her Majesty the Queen in Her Robes of State," from the painting by F. Winterhalter, undated
    - Stereoscopic color print of "Loading Our Canoes at the Landing," no. 1398, undated
    - Color print of "Prince Albert," by Currier and Ives, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - 4 color prints of "Stage Coaches of England," published by Sidney Z. Lucas, undated (Box 1)
    - Color print of a suited man with a top hat, undated
    - Color print of "The Late Miss Whitehead, the Bank Nunn", circa 1825
    - 25 Ogden's Guinea Gold Cigarette Cards, undated
    - 17 Ogden's Tab Cigarette Cards, undated
    - Photographs
      - Signed photograph of Aubrey Beardsley, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
      - Black and white snapshot of the entrance gateway to Tilbury Fort, undated (Box 1)
      - Studio portrait, mounted on board, of a costumed woman with a sword, Colby Photographers, Orala, Florida, 1879
      - Photograph of a sketch of a bearded man with the caption "O heliger Geift kehr buy uns ein.", undated
      - Photograph of a sketch of "Fleeta, controlling spirit of Mrs. K. S. Eggert, Clairvoyant, taken by Prof. Walla and Pet Anderson, as seen in spirit life," by Tuttle & Johnson, London, undated
      - Studio portrait of Princess Alice, by Mayall, London, undated
      - Studio portrait of two costumed Scotsmen, by Crowe and Rodgers, Stirling, undated
      - Photograph of the interior of Abbotsford Library, by G. W. Wilson & Co., Aberdeen, undated
      - Stereograph of a man seated behind a table, undated
      - Stereograph of "London Every Day Life," no. 6012 by B. W. Kilburn, Littleton, New Hampshire, undated
      - Stereograph of "England's 'Grand Old Man' - W. E. Gladstone," by Keystone View Co, 1899
      - Stereograph of "Colonial Troops from India and Australia in the Coronation Procession, London," no. 15033 by B. W. Kilburn, Littleton, New Hampshire, undated
      - 22 photographs of "Ectoplasmic Apparitions," involving a double-exposure technique, undated
    - Engravings
      - Buckingham Palace, drawn and engraved by N. Whittock, undated
      - "H. R. H. The Duke of York in Uniform of Lieutenant of the British Navy", undated (Box 1)
      - "Aylmer Bourke Lambert, Esq... One of the Vice Presidents of the Linnean Society," engraved by W. Evans from a drawing by H. Edridge, circa 1810 (Box 6)
      - "Sir Robert Harry Inglis Bart," engraved by J. Jenkins, undated (Box 1)
      - "Prince Albert at the age of four" and "Prince Albert at the age of twenty," engraved by William Holl, undated
      - "Robert Vernon, Esq.," engraved by W. H. Mote, undated
      - "Her Most Gracious Majesty the Queen," engraved by H. T. Ryall, undated
      - "His Most Royal Highness the Prince Consort," engraved by D. J. Pound, undated
      - Prince Albert, undated (Box 1)
      - "Simon Lord Lovat, beheaded 1747", undated
      - "The Election: Humours of an Election Entertainment," engraved by T. E. Nicholson, undated
      - "Mineralogy," engraved by Wilson Lowry, 1802 January 2
    - Postcards
      - 3 "giant" postcards - Cockington Village; Torquay, Tor Abbey Sands; and Natural Arch, undated
      - 8 postcards of "Wax Effigies in Westminster Abbey", undated
      - 20 postcards depicting various scenes and people, 1882-1915, undated
        Scope and Contents
        The following are included: - The Stone of Destiny, Valentine & Son, London - Tombstone of Peter Isnell (died 1811 March 31) - American Indian and explorer - L. L. A. A. R. R. I Principi di Savoia - Crown Princess Louise - Crown Prince Olau - Norwegian king and queen - Koningin Wilhelmina - Charles II, Westminster Abbey - Earl of Leicester - Prince Charles Edward Stuart - Peers paying homage to the king - Chair from the Victoria and Albert museum - Needlework chair seat from the Victoria and Albert museum - The Great Well Carisbrooke - Charles Dickens and characters calendar from 1911 - "Wishing you a joyful Easter-tide," 1915 April 2 (postmark) - Arm chair from the Victoria and Albert museum - Drawing of a man with a top hat, 1882 July 27 (postmark) - "Merry Goes the Time," by O. Stockman for Pearl's milk-blended butter
    - Advertising Material
      - 2 tradesman's cards, undated
      - 2 bookmarks - Great Western Railway, "Holiday Haunts," and Northern of London and Aberdeen Fire, Life, Accident, and Burglary Insurance Co., undated
      - 2 labels - Rose Soap and Belfast Linens, undated
      - Price list of European newspapers and magazines, 1879
      - 9 "Heroes of History" cards from Miners Extra Smoking Tobacco and Royal Bengals Little Cigars, undated
      - 3 cigar bands, undated
      - 27 Kensitas Cigarette "cards" - flags of the British empire, printed on satin, undated
    - Portraits, undated (Box 1)
      The following are included: - Princess Victoria at 18 - Queen Victoria from the Royal London Wax Museum - Mark Twain - Water-color portrait believed to be the lost miniature of Shelley by Edward Ellerker Williams - Professor Tyndall - Caricature of "Bobby Lowe" - Sir Charles Wheatstone - The Earl of Rosslyn, Mr. James Erskine - Admiral Inglefield - The Bishop of Ripon - Caricature of Mr. J. Ashby Sterry, the lazy minstrel - His Majesty the King, 1911 - The King and Queen shortly after their marriage - King George as Vice-Admiral in 1903 - View from behind of a seated man wearing a hat - Caricature of "Rivals Thackeray and Dickens" - The late Napolean III, Ex-Emperor of France - Winston Churchill - Will Carleton, author of "Betsey and I are Out" - Queen Victoria, one month before her death (1901) - George Charles, 7th Duke of Marlborough; Frances Anne, Duchess of Marlborough - Queen Victoria, William Gladstone, The Marquis of Salisbury, Benjamin Disraeli (separate portraits on one clipping) - Lord Randolph Churchill and his caricature - Lord Randolph S. Churchill, circa 1874; Jennie R. Churchill (separate portraits on one clipping) - Lord Randolph Churchill, 1893
    - Portraits - Oversize, 1952, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
      The following are included: - The Right Hon. Sir Alexander Cockburn - Simon Ward, actor, as Winston Churchill - Winston Churchill and Harry S. Truman, 1952 - The Right Hon. William Evart Gladstone, Premier of England - Lord Lytton - The Right Hon. John Bright, M. P. - Mark Twain, with a list of some famous quotes - "The Old Queen"
    - Other, undated (Box 1)
      The following are included: - Black and white print of "Stanley shooting the rapids of the Congo" - Black and white print of "Rosa Bonhuer" - Black and white print of "The Prodigal Son" - Black and white print of "York and Lancaster - The White and Red Roses" - Black and white print of "Dr. Johnson's Penance" - Black and white print of "Tennyson in his library" - Black and white print of "Gordon attacked by El Mahdi's Arabs" - Black and white print of "The death of Chatterton, the young poet" - Black and white print of "Last Scene of All," plate 6 of Hogarth's Marriage a la Mode - Black and white print of "I love thee because thou art daring" - Black and white print of "Gladstone's first home rule bill" - Black and white print of a tower house on a cliff in moonlight - Black and white print of "But he gave us glory" - Black and white print of "The Fatal Duel," plate 5 of Hogarth's Marriage a la Mode - Small print of street vendors - Small print of schoolboy - Color reproduction of "Charlie the Cox" - Black and white print of "Ludgate Circus," circa 1860 - Black and white print of "The Observatory, Greenwich" - Black and white reproduction of the front cover of A Christmas Carol by Charles Dickens - 2 black and white reproductions of the title page of A Christmas Carol by Charles Dickens - Color print of "Knighthood: Mantles and Insignia of the Principal British Orders of Knighthood" - Black and white print of Eaton, Lower School - Black and white print of the boys at Dotheboys Hall, where Nicholas Nickleby was master - Color print of "The White and the Red Rose" - Illustrated poem in color, "The Happy Home" - Color print of "The Atlantic Telegraph" - "The Dying Words and Confession of Elias Lucas and Mary Reader" - "Education...at Bowe's Academy," reproduction of an advertisting notice - "Mrs. Hartley's School for Young Ladies," reproduction of an advertisting notice
    - Other, 1838-1971, undated (Box 1)
      The following are included: - Black and white print of "View of a Pit" and "Bottom of a Shaft" - Black and white print of "The Royal Palace of Justice, London" - Clipping from the New York Times: "Fisk Jubilee Singers performing before Queen Victoria," 1971 September 30 (2 copies) - Photocopy of clipping: "Fisk Jubilee Singers performing before Queen Victoria" - Black and white print of "The Queen Leaving Buckingham Palace for the Opening of the Great Exhibition" - Black and white print of "The Prince's Vigil" - Illustrations of Sherlock Holmes from "A Scandal in Bohemia," printed in Strand Magazine - Illustration of two Victorian gentleman (by Beardsley?) - Color print of "Lord Mayor Hosts the Young Queen at Guild Hall" - Color print of "Victorian Travel by Railroad" - Color print of illustrated alphabet, letters W-Z, with verse - Color print of "The Salvation Army Social Campaign" - Color print of "Victoria's Coronation in Westminster Abbey," circa 1838 - Color print of "The Cutler's Monthly Journal of London and Paris Fashions for December 1856" - "Hogarth House Gem Pocket Library," reproduction of an advertisement - Color print of "And now let Mr. Lambkin speak for himself..." - Black and white print of "Battle School, Sussex," 1847 - Black and white print of "Trinity College," 1842 - Black and white print of "London Foundling Hospital" - Black and white print of "Staple's Inn" - Black and white print of "Street Front of the Fleet Prison" - Black and white print of "Courtyard in the Fleet Prison" - Black and white print of "Wedding in the Fleet" - Black and white print of "The Last Remains of the Fleet Prison" - Black and white print of "Banard's Inn" - Black and white print of "There's life in the old dog yet," mounted - Black and white print of "The Wood-Engraver" - Black and white print of "Nobility" - Black and white print of "December, as depicted by George Cruikshank in the comic almanack for 1835" - Black and white print of "The Lecture room at the Royal Institution, London" - Black and white print of "Holyrood Palace, Edinburgh"
    - Other - Oversize, 1855, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
      The following are included: - Map of the seat of war in Europe, showing the principal strategic points on the Rhine and the Coast - "Bank of London, Head Office, Threadneedle Street," from the Illustrated London News, 1855 December 29 - Color print of "P. T. Barnum's Greatest Show on Earth and The Great London Circus Combined with Jumbo" - Black and white print of "The Fisherman's Daughter" - Black and white print of "The Connoisseurs" - Black and white print of "Undine" - Clipping of Camden Place, Chiselhurst, residence of Napolean III
    - Other - Oversize, 1874-1875 (Box 11 (Oversize))
      The following are included: - "Entry of the Prince of Wales into Baroda," from the extra supplement to the Illustrated London News, 1875 December 18 - "A Wild Boar Hunt," from the Illustrated London News, 1874 September 19
  - Printed - Newspaper, Magazine, and Book Clippings
    - "The Queen of a Century! Victoria," mounted on board, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Lady with the Lamp - Florence Nightengale," mounted on board, undated
    - "The Novelist-Politician, Benjamin Disraeli," mounted on board, undated
    - "The Longest Reign in British History - Queen Victoria," mounted on board, undated
    - "Romantic Rebel - Lord Byron," mounted on board, undated
    - "For England and the Suez Canal - Benjamin Disraeli," mounted on board, undated
    - "Blood, Sweat and Tears - Winston L. S. Churchill," mounted on board, undated
    - "A Naked Flame of Natural Genius - Charles Dickens," mounted on board, undated
    - Printed material - Clippings, 1843-1904, undated (Box 1)
      The following are included: - War Supplement to The New York Times - Ancestry of King Edward VII and Queen Alexandra (photocopy) - "Rachel," by Florence Montgomery, The Universal Magazine, 1900 November - "Bridal Crowns," by Gamle Norge, The Universal Magazine - "Peeps into Women's Clubs," by Leily Bingen, The Universal Magazine - "Catherine Gladstone," by Philip Guedalla - "John Burns, L. C. C., M. P.," by W. B. Northrop, With Pen and Camera, 1904 - Clipping from Harper's Magazine about Mary Russel Mitford - 2 clippings about "Lord Chief Justice" - Clipping about "Black Rod" - Clipping about the "Royal Household" - Clipping about "Civil List" - Clipping about "The King's Champion" - Clipping about "Sargent-at-arms" - Clipping about "Ceremonies" - Clipping about "Lord Chamberlain" - Clipping about "Lord Great Chamberlain" - Clipping about "Chamberlain" - Clipping about "Marquess of Chalmondelay" - Clipping about "Coronet," with illustration - Clipping about "Clarenceaux" - Clipping about "College of Arms" - Clipping about "Church of England" - Clipping about "Cathedrals of Established Church of England" - Clipping about "The Lord High Chancellor of Great Britain" - Clipping about a mining explosion, 1843 April - "Handcuffs," by Maurince Moser, Strand Magazine, 1854
    - Printed material - Clippings, 1842-1973, undated
      The following are included: - "Wrapping up the Past," by Beryl Platts, Country Life, 1968 March 14 - "Airmail Flops," Daily Telegraph, 1973 February 2 - Clipping about "Geological Society" - Review of "Judaica," Havard University Press, 1973 February 16 - 2 clippings about "Sir James Emerson Tennent" - "The Art of Colin Hunter," by R. C. Trafford, Windsor Magazine, 1912 - "The Art of Henry Stacy Marks," by Austin Chester, Windsor Magazine - "Illustrated Interview No. 14 - Sir Frederick Leighton," Strand Magazine, 1892 - "Holman Hunt by the Dead Sea," by Christopher Neve, Country Life, 1969 April 3 - "Price 'Eddie's' Bride," The Illustrated American, 1891 December 12 - "Prince of Savants: Baron Alexander von Humboldt," by William Gardner, Country Life, 1969 September 11 - "On the Trail of the Vanishing 'Man of Letters,'" by Bruce Cook, The National Observer, 1969 September 8 - "Four Years with Whistler," by Edith Shaw, Apollo Magazine, 1968 March - "First Report of the Commissioners," The Athenaeum, 1842 May 7 - "A Merry Man of Windsor," by Charles Poore, The New York Times, 1967 August 10 - "The Ladies of Queen Victoria's Court," Strand Magazine, 1896 - "An Open Letter to the American Public," by Charles Garvice, 1898 August 30 - "For the First Time...A Museum Features Whistler's Work," by Douglas M. Davis, The National Observer, 1968 January 22 - "Tough Dandy," Newsweek, 1968 January 22 - Clipping about Whistler's mother-in-law (Mrs. John Birnie Philip) - 2 miniature copies of Daily Telegraph Courier, London, 1855 June 29 - "General Patton's Speech to His Third Army Prior to D-Day" - Review of Reviews, 1897 December - Clipping with an anecdote about Whistler - "A Letter from Lord Macaulay," 1857 May 23
    - Printed material - Clippings, 1969-1973, undated
      The following are included: - "The Prodigal Son," by John M. Swan - Clipping about "Mineralogical Society" - Clipping about "Meterorological Society" - Clipping about "Primrose League" - "The Privy Council," by A. F. Pollard - Clipping about "Parliament" - Clipping about "Judge Advocate General" - Clipping about "Judges" - Clipping about "Law Courts," with illustration - Clipping about "Chancellors" - Clipping about "Lord Keeper of the Great Seal" - Clipping about "King's Remembrances" - Clipping about "Justice of the Peace" - Clipping about "Primrose League" - Clipping about "Lord President of the Council" - Clipping about "Postmaster-General" - Clipping about "Lord Mayor" - Clipping defining "Liberal" - Clipping about "Lyon's Inn" - Clipping about "Home Office," with illustration - Clipping describing the office of "Prime Minister" - Clipping about "British Diplomatic Service" - Clipping describing the title "Honorable" - Clipping describing the title "Knight" - Clipping describing the title "Baronet" - Clipping describing the title "Earl" - Clipping describing the title "Viscount" - Clipping describing the title "Baron" - Clipping describing the title "Duke" - Clipping describing the title "Marquis" - Clipping about "Peerage" - Clemens, Walter: Book review of The Victorian Country House, by M. Giroud, 1972 December 25 - Book review of Miss Dizzy, by Mollie Hardwick, 1972 August 25 - Anecdote about titles of nobility - Book review of Victorian Children, by Robert Melville, Newsweek, 1973 February 26 - Book review of The Aesthetic Movement, by Robin Spencer, 1972 October 13 - Cocks, Jay: Film review of "Lady Caroline Lamb," Time, 1973 February 26 - "The First English Circus," by Peggy Hickman, Country Life, 1969 December 4
    - Printed material - Oversize, 1850-1968, undated (Box 6)
      The following are included: - "The Czar: The Preparations for His Coronation in May Next," The Evening Star, Philadelphia, 1882 February 16. - "An Animal Artist of 100 Years Ago: Abraham Cooper," by Stella A. Walker, Country Life, 1968 December 19. - "Gradations in the Sin of Unbelief: A Sermon Preached by Rev. L. W. Bacon," 1869 September 29 - "Our Foreign Correspondent: Letter no. XII," London, 1869 October 23 - "London Letter: A Dickens Ferment" - "Owen Meredith (Lord Lytton)," The Illustrated American, 1891 December 12 - "Miss Rotchford Tells of Three Collections at Texas University," by Fannie Rotchford, Dallas Times Herald - "From London Town to Oxford's Spires" - The New York Times Book Review, 1967 July 16 - "The Tide of Emigration to the U. S. and to the British Colonies," Illustrated London News, 1850 July 6
    - Printed material - Oversize, undated (Box 10 (Oversize))
      The following are included: - "Whistler in Chelsea," by Phillippe Jullian - "Mark Twain in Paris or Innocents Abroad," by Phillippe Jullian
    - Scrapbook on the Boer War, mostly clipped from Country Life, undated (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook of miscellaneous material, mostly clipped from Illustrated London News, 1878-1879 (Box 7 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook of miscellaneous material, mostly clipped from Illustrated London News, 1894-1897 (Box 7 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook of pictorial material, circa 1872-1878 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - Benjamin Disraeli
    - Portraits, 1861-1869, undated (Box 1)
      The following are included: - Photograph by Kilburn of Mr. Disraeli, [London, 1861] - Photograph by Mayall Photographers of Disraeli, London, [1869] - Portrait reproduction of "Benjamin Disraeli at Twenty-Eight" - Color etching of Benjamin Disraeli by Vinaeli - Engraving of Benjamin Disraeli - Engraving, "The Right Hon. Benjamin Disraeli, Earl of Beaconsfield" - Engraving, "The Right Hon. Benjamin Disraeli, Earl of Beaconsfield," by W. Roffe
    - Clippings - portraits, pictures, texts, 1877-1886, undated